<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!-- edited with XMLSPY v2004 rel. 2 U (http://www.xmlspy.com) by lcollins (Firaxis Games) -->
<!-- Sid Meier's Civilization 4 -->
<!-- Copyright Firaxis Games 2005 -->
<!-- -->
<!-- Game Text - New -->
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_MACCABEE</Tag>
		<English>Maccabee</English>
		<French>Macchab%C3%A9es</French>
		<German>Makkab%C3%A4er</German>
		<Italian>Maccabei</Italian>
		<Spanish>Maccabee</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
    	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_MACCABEE_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>The Maccabees were a Jewish national liberation movement that fought for independence from Antiochus IV Epiphanes.  The Maccabees founded the Hasmonean Dynasty of Israel.  In 167 BC, after Antiochus forbade Jewish practice, a priest from Modiin, Mattathias the Hasmonean, sparked a revolt by refusing to worship Greek gods.  After Mattathias’s death, his son Judah Maccabee led an army of Jews against the Seleucid Dynasty.  The term Maccabees is used to describe the army of Judah Maccabee. [PARAGRAPH:1] The revolt included many individual battles.  In many, the Maccabeean forces won victory for their use of guerrilla tactics.  After the revolt, the Maccabees cleansed the temple, and declared Judah Maccabee a priest.  A Syrian army was sent to destroy the revolt, but returned after the death of Antiochus. [PARAGRAPH:1] After the revolt, the Maccabees were unsure whether to continue fighting, seeing their military success in the revolt.  Those who continued to fight were led by Judah Maccabee.  Judah Maccabee died in 160 BC in battle.  Judah was succeeded by his younger brother Jonathan, who was already a high priest.  Jonathan made treaties with foreign nations, causing more disputes between those who wanted religious freedom over political power.  In 142 BC, Jonathan died.  He was succeeded by the last son of Mattathias, Simon.  That same year, Demetrius, king of Syria, granted the Jews independence from Syria and Simon went on to found the Hasmonean dynasty. [PARAGRAPH:1] Every year, Jews celebrate Hannukah to celebrate and recognize Judah Maccabee’s victory over the Seleucids and related miracles.</English>
		<French>Le Maccabees étaient un mouvement national juif de libération qui a combattu pour l'indépendance d'Antiochus IV Epiphanes. Le Maccabees a fondé la dynastie de Hasmonean de l'Israel. Dans 167 AVANT JÉSUS CHRIST, après qu'Antiochus ait interdit la pratique juive, un prêtre de Modiin, Mattathias le Hasmonean, a étincelé une révolte en refusant d'adorer les dieux grecs. Après la mort de Mattathias, son fils Judah Maccabee a mené une armée des juifs contre la dynastie de Seleucid. Le terme Maccabees est employé pour décrire l'armée de Judah Maccabee. [PARAGRAPH : 1] La révolte a inclus beaucoup de différentes batailles. Dans beaucoup, les forces de Maccabeean ont gagné la victoire pour leur usage de la tactique de guérillero. Après la révolte, le Maccabees a nettoyé le temple, et a déclaré Judah Maccabee un prêtre. Une armée syrienne a été envoyée pour détruire la révolte, mais est retournée après la mort d'Antiochus. [PARAGRAPH : 1] Après la révolte, le Maccabees étaient incertain si continuer de combattre, voyant leur succès militaire dans la révolte. Ceux qui ont continué à combattre ont été menés par Judah Maccabee. Judah Maccabee est mort dans 160 AVANT JÉSUS CHRIST dans la bataille. Judah a été réussi par son plus jeune frère Jonathan, qui était déjà un haut prêtre. Jonathan a fait des traités avec des nations étrangères, causant plus de conflits entre ceux qui ont voulu la puissance politique d'excédent religieux de liberté. Dans 142 AVANT JÉSUS CHRIST, Jonathan est mort. Il a été réussi par le dernier fils de Mattathias, Simon. Que la même année, Demetrius, roi de la Syrie, a accordé aux juifs l'indépendance de Syrie et Simon a continué à a trouvé la dynastie de Hasmonean. [PARAGRAPH : 1] Chaque année, juifs célèbrent Hannukah pour célébrer et identifier la victoire de Judah Maccabee sur le Seleucids et les miracles relatifs.</French>
		<German>Das Maccabees waren eine jüdische nationale Befreiungbewegung, die für Unabhängigkeit von Antiochus IV Epiphanes kämpfte. Das Maccabees gründete die Hasmonean Dynastie von Israel. In 167 BC, nachdem Antiochus jüdische Praxis verbot, funkte ein Priester von Modiin, Mattathias das Hasmonean, ein Aufruhr, indem er ablehnte, griechische Götter anzubeten. Nach Tod Mattathiass führte sein Sohn Judah Maccabee eine Armee der Juden gegen die Seleucid Dynastie. Die Bezeichnung Maccabees wird verwendet, um die Armee von Judah Maccabee zu beschreiben. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Der Aufruhr schloß viele einzelne Schlachten ein. In vielen gewannen die Maccabeean Kräfte Sieg für ihren Gebrauch von Bandenkämpfertaktiken. Nach dem Aufruhr reinigte das Maccabees den Bügel und erklärte Judah Maccabee ein Priester. Eine syrische Armee wurde gesendet, um den Aufruhr zu zerstören, aber zurückging nach dem Tod von Antiochus. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Nach dem Aufruhr waren das Maccabees unsicher, ob man fortfährt zu kämpfen und ihren militärischen Erfolg im Aufruhr sieht. Die, die fortfuhren zu kämpfen, wurden von Judah Maccabee geführt. Judah Maccabee starb in 160 BC in der Schlacht. Judah wurde von seinem jüngeren Bruder Jonathan gefolgt, der bereits ein hoher Priester war. Jonathan bildete Verträge mit den fremden Nationen und verursachte mehr Debatten zwischen denen, die politische Energie des frommen Freiheit überschusses wünschten. In 142 BC, starb Jonathan. Er wurde vom letzten Sohn von Mattathias, Simon gefolgt. Daß das gleiche Jahr, Demetrius, König von Syrien, den Juden Unabhängigkeit von Syrien und von Simon bewilligte, gingen an zu fanden die Hasmonean Dynastie. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Jedes Jahr, Juden feiern Hannukah, um Judah Maccabees Sieg über dem Seleucids und den in Verbindung stehenden Wundern zu feiern und zu erkennen.</German>
		<Italian>Il Maccabees era un movimento nazionale ebreo di liberazione che ha combattuto per indipendenza da Antiochus IV Epiphanes. Il Maccabees ha fondato il Dynasty di Hasmonean dell'Israele. In 167 BC, dopo che Antiochus proibisse alla pratica ebrea, un priest da Modiin, Mattathias il Hasmonean, ha scintillato una sommossa rifiutando di adorare i dii greci. Dopo la morte del Mattathias, il suo figlio Judah Maccabee ha condotto un esercito degli ebrei contro il Dynasty di Seleucid. Il termine Maccabees è usato per descrivere l'esercito di Judah Maccabee. [PARAGRAPH: 1] La sommossa ha incluso molte diverse battaglie. In molti, le forze di Maccabeean hanno vinto la vittoria per il loro uso delle tattiche del guerrigliero. Dopo la sommossa, il Maccabees ha pulito il tempiale ed ha dichiarato Judah Maccabee un priest. Un esercito siriano è stato trasmesso per distruggere la sommossa, ma ha rinviato dopo la morte di Antiochus. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Dopo la sommossa, il Maccabees era incerto se continuare il combattimento, vedente il loro successo militare nella sommossa. Coloro che ha continuato a combattere sono stati condotti da Judah Maccabee. Judah Maccabee è morto BC in 160 nella battaglia. Judah è stato riuscito dal suo fratello più giovane Jonathan, che era già un alto priest. Jonathan ha fatto i trattati con le nazioni straniere, causanti più dispute fra coloro che ha desiderato l'alimentazione politica dell'eccedenza religiosa di libertà. In 142 BC, Jonathan morto. È stato riuscito dall'ultimo figlio di Mattathias, Simon. Che lo stesso anno, Demetrius, re della Siria, ha assegnato agli ebrei l'indipendenza dalla Siria e da Simon ha continuato a ha trovato il dynasty di Hasmonean. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Ogni anno, ebrei celebra Hannukah per celebrare e riconoscere la vittoria del Judah Maccabee sopra il Seleucids ed i miracoli relativi.</Italian>
		<Spanish>El Maccabees era un movimiento nacional judío de la liberación que luchó para la independencia de Antiochus IV Epiphanes. El Maccabees fundó la dinastía de Hasmonean de Israel. En 167 A.C., después de que Antiochus prohibiera práctica judía, un sacerdote de Modiin, Mattathias el Hasmonean, chispeó una rebelión rechazando adorar a dioses griegos. Después de la muerte de Mattathias, su hijo Judah Maccabee condujo a ejército de judíos contra la dinastía de Seleucid. El término Maccabees se utiliza para describir al ejército de Judah Maccabee. [PARAGRAPH: 1] La rebelión incluyó muchas batallas individuales. En muchos, las fuerzas de Maccabeean ganaron la victoria para su uso de las táctica del guerrilla. Después de la rebelión, el Maccabees limpió el templo, y declaró a Judah Maccabee un sacerdote. Enviaron para destruir la rebelión, pero volvió un ejército sirio después de la muerte de Antiochus. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Después de la rebelión, el Maccabees era inseguro si continuar luchando, viendo su éxito militar en la rebelión. A Judah Maccabee condujeron los que continuaron luchando. Judah Maccabee murió en 160 A.C. en batalla. A su hermano más joven Jonatán tuvo éxito a Judah, que era ya sacerdote alto. Jonatán hizo tratados con las naciones extranjeras, causando más conflictos entre los que desearon energía política del excedente religioso de la libertad. En 142 A.C., Jonatán muerto. Al hijo pasado de Mattathias lo tuvo éxito, Simon. Que el mismo año, Demetrius, rey de Siria, concedió a judíos independencia de Siria y de Simon fue encendido a encontró la dinastía de Hasmonean. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Cada año, judíos celebra Hannukah para celebrar y para reconocer la victoria de Judah Maccabee sobre el Seleucids y los milagros relacionados.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIQUE_NAME_A1</Tag>
		<English>AA</English>
		<French>
			<Text>AA</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>AA</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>AA</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>AA</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIQUE_NAME_A2</Tag>
		<English>BB</English>
		<French>
			<Text>BB</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>BB</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>BB</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>BB</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIQUE_NAME_A3</Tag>
		<English>CC</English>
		<French>
			<Text>CC</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>CC</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>CC</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>CC</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIQUE_NAME_A4</Tag>
		<English>DD</English>
		<French>
			<Text>DD</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>DD</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>DD</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>DD</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIQUE_NAME_A5</Tag>
		<English>EE</English>
		<French>
			<Text>EE</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>EE</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>EE</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>EE</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIQUE_NAME_A6</Tag>
		<English>FF</English>
		<French>
			<Text>FF</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>FF</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>FF</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>FF</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIQUE_NAME_A7</Tag>
		<English>GG</English>
		<French>
			<Text>GG</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>GG</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>GG</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>GG</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIQUE_NAME_A8</Tag>
		<English>HH</English>
		<French>
			<Text>HH</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>HH</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>HH</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>HH</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIQUE_NAME_A9</Tag>
		<English>II</English>
		<French>
			<Text>II</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>II</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>II</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>II</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIQUE_NAME_A0</Tag>
		<English>JJ</English>
		<French>
			<Text>JJ</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>JJ</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>JJ</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>JJ</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIQUE_NAME_B1</Tag>
		<English>KK</English>
		<French>
			<Text>KK</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>KK</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>KK</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>KK</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIQUE_NAME_B2</Tag>
		<English>LL</English>
		<French>
			<Text>LL</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>LL</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>LL</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>LL</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIQUE_NAME_B3</Tag>
		<English>MM</English>
		<French>
			<Text>MM</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>MM</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>MM</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>MM</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIQUE_NAME_B4</Tag>
		<English>NN</English>
		<French>
			<Text>NN</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>NN</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>NN</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>NN</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIQUE_NAME_B5</Tag>
		<English>OO</English>
		<French>
			<Text>OO</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>OO</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>OO</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>OO</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIQUE_NAME_B6</Tag>
		<English>PP</English>
		<French>
			<Text>PP</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>PP</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>PP</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>PP</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIQUE_NAME_B7</Tag>
		<English>QQ</English>
		<French>
			<Text>QQ</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>QQ</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>QQ</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>QQ</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIQUE_NAME_B8</Tag>
		<English>RR</English>
		<French>
			<Text>RR</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>RR</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>RR</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>RR</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIQUE_NAME_B9</Tag>
		<English>SS</English>
		<French>
			<Text>SS</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>SS</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>SS</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>SS</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIQUE_NAME_B0</Tag>
		<English>TT</English>
		<French>
			<Text>TT</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>TT</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>TT</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>TT</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIQUE_NAME_C1</Tag>
		<English>UU</English>
		<French>
			<Text>UU</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>UU</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>UU</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>UU</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIQUE_NAME_C2</Tag>
		<English>VV</English>
		<French>
			<Text>VV</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>VV</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>VV</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>VV</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIQUE_NAME_C3</Tag>
		<English>WW</English>
		<French>
			<Text>WW</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>WW</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>WW</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>WW</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIQUE_NAME_C4</Tag>
		<English>XX</English>
		<French>
			<Text>XX</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>XX</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>XX</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>XX</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIQUE_NAME_C5</Tag>
		<English>YY</English>
		<French>
			<Text>YY</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>YY</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>YY</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>YY</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIQUE_NAME_C6</Tag>
		<English>ZZ</English>
		<French>
			<Text>ZZ</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>ZZ</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>ZZ</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>ZZ</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIQUE_NAME_C7</Tag>
		<English>AAA</English>
		<French>
			<Text>AAA</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>AAA</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>AAA</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>AAA</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIQUE_NAME_C8</Tag>
		<English>BBB</English>
		<French>
			<Text>BBB</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>BBB</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>BBB</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>BBB</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIQUE_NAME_C9</Tag>
		<English>CCC</English>
		<French>
			<Text>CCC</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>CCC</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>CCC</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>CCC</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIQUE_NAME_C0</Tag>
		<English>DDD</English>
		<French>
			<Text>DDD</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>DDD</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>DDD</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>DDD</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>