<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!-- edited with XMLSPY v2004 rel. 2 U (http://www.xmlspy.com) by lcollins (Firaxis Games) -->
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_LEONIDAS</Tag>
		<English>Leonidas</English>
		<French>Leonidas</French>
		<German>Leonidas</German>
		<Italian>Leonidas</Italian>
		<Spanish>Leonidas</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_HIRAM</Tag>
		<English>Hiram</English>
		<French>Hiram</French>
		<German>Hiram</German>
		<Italian>Hiram</Italian>
		<Spanish>Hiram</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_DAVID</Tag>
		<English>David</English>
		<French>David</French>
		<German>David</German>
		<Italian>David</Italian>
		<Spanish>David</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_SUPPILULIUMA_I</Tag>
		<English>Suppiluliuma I</English>
		<French>Suppiluliuma I</French>
		<German>Schuppiluliuma I</German>
		<Italian>Suppiluliuma I</Italian>
		<Spanish>Shubiluliuma I</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_SUPPILULIUMA_I_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[H1]Suppiluliuma I[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]King of the Hittites[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lived: [\BOLD]c.1358 - 1323 BC[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:1][BOLD]Background:[\BOLD][PARAGRAPH:1]Despite the close relationship between Suppiluliuma and his father, Tudhaliya II, Suppiluliuma would not succeed him to the throne.  Instead, his brother Tudhaliya III would become king of the Hittites.  At this, Suppiluliuma was quite disappointed because he felt that he should receive the throne after all he had done to advise his father.  Suppiluliuma had goals for himself as king, and fighting broke out between the brothers and their supporters.  The fighting ended in the death of Tudhaliya. [PARAGRAPH:1] The death of Tudhaliya paved the way for the accession of Suppiluliuma to the throne.  Suppiluliuma married a sister to the Hayasan king Hukkana, and his daughter Muwatti to Maskhuiluwa of the Arzawan state Mira.  The most prominent of  the many successes of Suppiluliuma was his battles with the Mitanni Kingdom.  He reduced the lands of the Mitanni to a client state under the rule of his son-in-law Shattiwazza.  Suppiluliuma then took advantage of the disorderly reign of the Egyptian Pharaoh Akhenaton.  He captured much of the Egyptian territories in Syria.  [PARAGRAPH: 1] The success of Suppiluliuma encouraged the widow of the Egyptian king Nibhuruyira to write him and ask him to send one of her sons to marry her and rule Egypt.  Suppiluliuma dispatched one of his ambassadors to Egypt to investigate, who reported that the situation was accurately described.  Much to the disappointment of Suppiluliuma, his son Banana was murdered on his way to Egypt, and thus the marriage never occurred.  The now furious Suppiluliuma unleashed his armies against the vassal states of Egypt in Canaan and Northern Syria.  He captured much of this territory, but it brought plague to the Hittite heartland causing the deaths of Suppiluliuma and his successor Arnuwanda II.  </English>
		<French>[H1]Suppiluliuma I[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Roi d'Hittites[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Dates :[\BOLD]c.1358 - 1323[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:1][BOLD]Biographie :[\BOLD][PARAGRAPH:1]Despite the close relationship between Suppiluliuma and his father, Tudhaliya II, Suppiluliuma would not succeed him to the throne.  Instead, his brother Tudhaliya III would become king of the Hittites.  At this, Suppiluliuma was quite disappointed because he felt that he should receive the throne after all he had done to advise his father.  Suppiluliuma had goals for himself as king, and fighting broke out between the brothers and their supporters.  The fighting ended in the death of Tudhaliya. [PARAGRAPH:1] The death of Tudhaliya paved the way for the accession of Suppiluliuma to the throne.  Suppiluliuma married a sister to the Hayasan king Hukkana, and his daughter Muwatti to Maskhuiluwa of the Arzawan state Mira.  The most prominent of  the many successes of Suppiluliuma was his battles with the Mitanni Kingdom.  He reduced the lands of the Mitanni to a client state under the rule of his son-in-law Shattiwazza.  Suppiluliuma then took advantage of the disorderly reign of the Egyptian Pharaoh Akhenaton.  He captured much of the Egyptian territories in Syria.  [PARAGRAPH: 1] The success of Suppiluliuma encouraged the widow of the Egyptian king Nibhuruyira to write him and ask him to send one of her sons to marry her and rule Egypt.  Suppiluliuma dispatched one of his ambassadors to Egypt to investigate, who reported that the situation was accurately described.  Much to the disappointment of Suppiluliuma, his son Banana was murdered on his way to Egypt, and thus the marriage never occurred.  The now furious Suppiluliuma unleashed his armies against the vassal states of Egypt in Canaan and Northern Syria.  He captured much of this territory, but it brought plague to the Hittite heartland causing the deaths of Suppiluliuma and his successor Arnuwanda II.  </French>
		<German>[H1]Schuppiluliuma I[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]König von Hethiter[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lebte:[\BOLD]c.1358 - 1323 BC[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:1][BOLD]Hintergrund:[\BOLD][PARAGRAPH:1]Trotz der engen Beziehung zwischen Suppiluliuma und seinem Vater, Tudhaliya II, Suppiluliuma würde nicht gelingen, ihn auf den Thron. Stattdessen, seinem Bruder Tudhaliya III würde König der Hethiter. Auf dieser Suppiluliuma war sehr enttäuscht, weil er glaubte, daß er den Thron erhalten, nachdem alles, was er getan hatte zu beraten seines Vaters. Suppiluliuma hatte Ziele für sich selbst als König, und die Kämpfe zwischen den Brüdern und ihren Anhängern. Dem Ende der Kampfhandlungen, in der Tod von Tudhaliya. [ABSATZ: 1] Der Tod von Tudhaliya ebnete den Weg für den Beitritt von Suppiluliuma auf dem Thron. Suppiluliuma heiratete eine Schwester des Königs Hayasan Hukkana, und seine Tochter Muwatti zu Maskhuiluwa der Arzawan Staat Mira. Die prominentesten der vielen Erfolge der Suppiluliuma war seine Auseinandersetzungen mit dem Königreich Mitanni. Er reduziert das Land der Mitanni an einen Kunden Staat unter der Herrschaft seines Sohnes - in der Rechtsprechung Shattiwazza. Suppiluliuma dann nutzten die Unordnung Herrschaft des ägyptischen Pharao Echnaton. Er erfasste einen Großteil der ägyptischen Gebiete in Syrien. [ABSATZ: 1] Der Erfolg der Suppiluliuma ermutigt die Witwe des ägyptischen Königs Nibhuruyira zu schreiben und ihn bitten, ihn zu senden einer ihrer Söhne zu heiraten und Regel Ägypten. Suppiluliuma versandt 01 seiner Botschafter in Ägypten zu untersuchen, die berichteten, dass die Situation genau beschrieben. Sehr zur Enttäuschung von Suppiluliuma, sein Sohn ermordet Banane auf dem Weg nach Ägypten, und damit die Ehe nie aufgetreten. Die nunmehr wütend Suppiluliuma entfesselt seine Armeen gegen die Vasallen Staaten von Ägypten in Kanaan und Nordirland Syrien. Er erfasst viel von diesem Gebiet, aber es brachte Pest der Hittite Kernland, die den Tod von Suppiluliuma und seine Nachfolger Arnuwanda II.</German>
		<Italian>[H1]Suppiluliuma I[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Re di Ittiti[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Vita:[\BOLD]c.1358 - 1323 BC[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:1][BOLD]Informazioni:[\BOLD][PARAGRAPH:1]Nonostante la stretta relazione tra Suppiluliuma e suo padre, Tudhaliya II Suppiluliuma non succedergli al trono. Invece, il fratello Tudhaliya III sarebbe diventato re degli Ittiti. A questo, Suppiluliuma era abbastanza deluso perché ha ritenuto che egli dovrebbe ricevere il trono, dopo tutto quello che aveva fatto a consigliare di suo padre. Suppiluliuma aveva obiettivi per se stesso come re, e sono scoppiati degli scontri tra i fratelli e le loro sostenitori. La battaglia si è conclusa con la morte di Tudhaliya. [PARAGRAFO: 1] La morte di Tudhaliya spianato la strada per l'adesione di Suppiluliuma al trono. Suppiluliuma sposato una sorella alla Hayasan Hukkana re, e la figlia di Muwatti Maskhuiluwa del Arzawan stato Mira. Il più importante dei tanti successi di Suppiluliuma è stata la battaglia con il Regno Mitanni. Ha ridotto le terre dei Mitanni a un client di Stato sotto il dominio del figlio in Shattiwazza legge. Suppiluliuma poi ha approfittato della disordinata regno del faraone egiziano Akhenaton. Egli ha catturato gran parte del territorio egiziano in Siria. [PARAGRAFO: 1] Il successo di Suppiluliuma incoraggiato la vedova del re egiziano Nibhuruyira a scrivere di lui e gli chiedo di inviare uno dei suoi figli per sposarla e regola l'Egitto. Suppiluliuma spediamo uno dei suoi ambasciatori in Egitto per indagare, che ha riferito che la situazione è stato accuratamente descritto. Molto per la delusione di Suppiluliuma, Banana suo figlio è stato assassinato nel suo cammino verso l'Egitto e, quindi, il matrimonio non si è verificato. L'ora furiosi Suppiluliuma scatenata contro gli eserciti il suo vassallo stati d'Egitto nel Canaan e la Siria settentrionale. Egli ha catturato gran parte di questo territorio, ma che ha portato alla peste Hittite cuore causando la morte di Suppiluliuma e il suo successore Arnuwanda II.</Italian>
		<Spanish>[H1]Shubiluliuma I[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Rey de Hititi[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Vivi&#243;:[\BOLD]c.1358 - 1323 BC[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:1][BOLD]Historia:[\BOLD][PARAGRAPH:1]A pesar de la estrecha relación existente entre Suppiluliuma y su padre, Tudhaliya II, Suppiluliuma no le sucediera en el trono. En cambio, su hermano Tudhaliya III se convertiría en rey de los hititas. En esto, Suppiluliuma era bastante decepcionado porque creía que debía percibir el trono después de todo lo que ha realizado para asesorar a su padre. Suppiluliuma tenía metas para sí mismo como rey, y la lucha entre los hermanos y sus partidarios. La lucha terminó en la muerte de Tudhaliya. [APARTADO: 1] La muerte de Tudhaliya allanó el camino para la adhesión de Suppiluliuma al trono. Suppiluliuma se casó con una hermana a la Hayasan Hukkana rey, y su hija Muwatti a Maskhuiluwa del estado Arzawan Mira. El más prominente de los muchos éxitos de Suppiluliuma fue su batallas con el Reino Mitanni. Que la reducción de las tierras de los Mitanni a un cliente estado bajo el imperio de su yerno Shattiwazza. Suppiluliuma luego se aprovecharon de la desorganización reinado del faraón egipcio Akhenaton. Capturó gran parte de los territorios de Egipto en Siria. [APARTADO: 1] El éxito de Suppiluliuma alentó a la viuda del rey egipcio Nibhuruyira escribir él y le invito a enviar a uno de sus hijos a casarse con ella y con el artículo Egipto. Suppiluliuma enviamos uno de sus embajadores a Egipto para investigar, en la que informó que la situación fue descrita con precisión. Mucho a la decepción de Suppiluliuma, Banana su hijo fue asesinado durante su viaje a Egipto, y, por tanto, el matrimonio nunca ha ocurrido. El ahora furioso Suppiluliuma desatado sus ejércitos contra los estados vasallos de Egipto en Canaán y en el norte de Siria. Capturó gran parte de ese territorio, sino que trajo la peste a la heteo corazón causando la muerte de Suppiluliuma y su sucesor Arnuwanda II.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_SUPPILULIUMA_I_1</Tag>
		<English>The mighty [OUR_CIV_SHORT] welcome you! Before you speak, remember that a man's thoughts are revealed in his speech.</English>
		<French>La puissante [OUR_CIV_SHORT] vous souhaite la bienvenue! Avant de parler, de ne pas oublier que la pensée d'un homme est révélé dans son discours.</French>
		<German>Der mächtige [OUR_CIV_SHORT] begrüße Sie! Bevor sie sprechen, erinnern, daß ein Mann seine Gedanken sind offenbart in seiner Rede.</German>
		<Italian>La possente [OUR_CIV_SHORT] benvenuto! Prima di parlare, ricordare che i pensieri di un uomo si rivela nel suo intervento.</Italian>
		<Spanish>La poderosa [OUR_CIV_SHORT] bienvenida! Antes de hablar, recuerde que los pensamientos de un hombre se puso de manifiesto en su discurso.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_ATTILA</Tag>
		<English>Attila</English>
		<French>Attila</French>
		<German>Attila</German>
		<Italian>Attila</Italian>
		<Spanish>Attila</Spanish>
 </TEXT>
 	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_DIDO</Tag>
		<English>Dido</English>
		<French>Dido</French>
		<German>Dido</German>
		<Italian>Dido</Italian>
		<Spanish>Dido</Spanish>
</TEXT> 
  	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_PORSENNA</Tag>
		<English>Lars Porsenna</English>
		<French>Lars Porsenna</French>
		<German>Lars Porsenna</German>
		<Italian>Lars Porsenna</Italian>
		<Spanish>Lars Porsenna</Spanish>
</TEXT> 
<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_VATAVELLI</Tag>
		<English>Vatavelli</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Vatavelli</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>Vatavelli</German>
		<Italian>Vatavelli</Italian>
		<Spanish>Vatavelli</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_KINDATTU</Tag>
		<English>Kindattu</English>
		<French>Kindattu</French>
		<German>Kindattu</German>
		<Italian>Kindattu</Italian>
		<Spanish>Kindattu</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_ASHUR</Tag>
		<English>Ashurbanipal</English>
		<French>Ashurbanipal</French>
		<German>Ashurbanipal</German>
		<Italian>Ashurbanipal</Italian>
		<Spanish>Ashurbanipal</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_ASHUR_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[H1]Ashurbanipal[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]King of Assyria[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lived: [\BOLD] c.685 - 627 BC[PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Background:[\BOLD][PARAGRAPH:1]Ashurbanipal, the son of Esarhaddon and Naqi'a-Zakutu, was the last great king of ancient Assyria. He is famous as one of the few kings in antiquity who could himself read and write. Assyrian sculpture reached its apogee under his rule (Northern palace and south-western palace at Nineveh, battle of Ulai). The Greeks knew him as Sardanapalos; Latin and other medieval texts refer to him as Sardanapalus. In the Bible he is called As(e)nappar or Osnapper (Ezra 4:10).[PARAGRAPH:1]During his rule, Assyrian splendour was not only visible in its military power, but also its culture and art. Ashurbanipal created "the first systematically collected library" at Nineveh, where he attempted to gather all cuneiform literature available by that time. A library was distinct from an archive: earlier repositories of documents had accumulated passively, in the course of administrative routine.[PARAGRAPH:1]Ashurbanipal was born toward the end of a fifteen-hundred-year period of Assyrian ascendancy. His name in Assyrian is Ashur-bani-apli (the god Ashur has made a[nother] son), affirming that he was not intended to stand in the line of royal accession.[PARAGRAPH:1]His father, Esarhaddon, youngest son of Sennacherib, had become heir when the crown prince, Ashur-nadin-shumi, was deposed by rebels from his position as vassal for Babylon. Esarhaddon was not the son of Sennacherib's queen, Tashmetum-sharrat, but of the West Semitic "palace woman" Zakutu, known by her native name, Naqi'a. The only queen known for Esarhaddon was Ashur-hamat, who died in 672 BC[PARAGRAPH:1]Ashurbanipal grew up in the small palace called bit reduti (house of succession), built by Sennacherib when he was crown prince in the northern quadrant of Nineveh. In 694, Sennacherib had completed the "Palace Without Rival" at the southwest corner of the acropolis, obliterating most of the older structures. The "House of Succession" had become the palace of Esarhaddon, the crown prince. In this house, Ashurbanipal's grandfather was assassinated by uncles identified only from the biblical account as Adrammelek and Sharezer. From this conspiracy, Esarhaddon emerged as king in 681. He proceeded to rebuild as his residence the bit masharti (weapons house, or arsenal). The "House of Succession" was left to his mother and the younger children, including Ashurbanipal.[PARAGRAPH:1]Hisinheritance of Essarhaddon not only included the throne but also his war with Egypt and its lords, the kings of Kush. In 667 he sent an army against it that defeated king Tharqa near Memphis, Ashurbanipal stayed at his capital in Nineveh. At the same time the Egyptian vassals rebelled and the Assyrian army had to crush them. All of the leaders were sent to Nineveh, only Necho I the Prince of Saïs, convinced the Assyrians of his loyalty and was sent back to become king of Egypt. After the death of Tharqa in 664 BC his nephew and successor Tantamani invaded southern Egypt and made Thebe his capital. In Memphis he defeated the other Egyptian princes and Necho may have died in the battle. Another army was sent by Ashurbanipal and again it succeeded in defeating the Kushites. Tantamani retreated to his homeland and stayed there. The Assyrian plundered Thebes and took much booty home with them. How the Assyrian interference in Egypt ended is not certain but Necho's son Psammetichus I gained independence while keeping his relations with Assyria friendly. An interessting Assyrian royal inscription tells us of how the Lydian king Gyges received dreams from the Assyrian god Ashur. The dreams told him that when he submitted to Ashurbanipal he would conquer his foes. After he sent his ambassadors to do so he was indeed able to defeat his Cimmerians enemies. But when he supported the rebellion of one of the Egyptian rebels his country was overrun by the Cilicians.[PARAGRAPH:1]For the time being the dual monarchy went well. For his assignment of his brothers, Ashrubanipal sent a statue of the divinity Marduk with him as sign of good will. Shamsh-shuma-ukin's powers were limited. He performed Babylonian rituals but the official building projects were still executed by his younger brother. During his first years Elam was still in peace as it was under his father. Ashurbanipal even claimed that he sent food supplies during a famine. Around 664 BC the situation changed and Urtaku the Elamite king attacked Babylonia by surprise. Assyria delayed in sending aid to Babylon, this could have been caused for two reasons: either the soothing messages of Elamite ambassadors or Ashurbanipal might simply not have been present at that time. Elamites retreated before the Assyrian troops and in the same year Urtaku died. Urtaku was succeeded by Teumman (Tempti-Khumma-In-Shushinak) who was not his legimate heir. So, many of Elamite princes had to flee from him to Ashurbanipal's court including Urtaku's oldest son Humban-nikash. In 658 BC/657 BC the two empires clashed again. The reason for this was the treasonous province of Gambulu in 664 acting against the Assyrians. Ashurbanipal finally decided to punish them for that. On the other hand, Teumman saw his authority threatened by Elamite princes at the Assyrian court and demanded their extradition. When the Assyrian forces invaded Elam a battle followed at the Ulaya river.[PARAGRAPH:1]Elam was defeated in the battle in which, according to Assyrian reliefs, Teumman committed suicide. Tempti-Khumma-In-Shushinak and Ashurbanipal installed Humban-nikash as king of Madaktu and another prince, Tammaritu, as king of the city Hidalu. Elam was considered as a new vassal of Assyria and so tribute was imposed upon him. With the Elamite problem solved the Assyrians could finally punish Gumbulu and seized its capital. The victorious army marched home taking with them the head of Teumman. In Nineveh, when the Elamite ambassadors saw the head they lost control; one tore out his beard and the other committed suicide but this wasn't enough. As further humiliation the head of the Elamite king was put on display at the port of Nineveh. The death and head of Teumman was depicted multiple times in the reliefs of Ashurbanipal's palace.[PARAGRAPH:1]During the final decade of his rule, Assyria was quite peaceful, but the country apparently faced a serious decline. Documentation from the last years of Ashurbanipal's reign is very scarce, and even the date of his death is not known for certain. The latest attestations of Ashurbanipal's reign are of his year 38 (631 BC), but according to later sources he reigned for 42 years (to 627 BC). Because of the chronological difficulties that arise with his death in 627 Ashurbanipal must have died at an earlier date (probably already in 631) or he could have reigned together with his son and successor Ashur-etil-ilani. Whatever may have been the case, after his death there was a power struggle. The contenders included Ashur-etil-ilani, his brother Sinsharishkun, general Sin-shumu-lishir, and the eventual new king of Babylon, Nabopolassar. Who fought against who is not certain.[PARAGRAPH1]Ashurbanipal is one of the most popular Assyrian kings, as his name is often used for boys within Assyrian communities today.</English>
		<French>[H1]Ashurbanipal[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]King of Assyria[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lived: [\BOLD] c.685 - 627 BC[PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Background:[\BOLD][PARAGRAPH:1]Ashurbanipal, the son of Esarhaddon and Naqi'a-Zakutu, was the last great king of ancient Assyria. He is famous as one of the few kings in antiquity who could himself read and write. Assyrian sculpture reached its apogee under his rule (Northern palace and south-western palace at Nineveh, battle of Ulai). The Greeks knew him as Sardanapalos; Latin and other medieval texts refer to him as Sardanapalus. In the Bible he is called As(e)nappar or Osnapper (Ezra 4:10).[PARAGRAPH:1]During his rule, Assyrian splendour was not only visible in its military power, but also its culture and art. Ashurbanipal created "the first systematically collected library" at Nineveh, where he attempted to gather all cuneiform literature available by that time. A library was distinct from an archive: earlier repositories of documents had accumulated passively, in the course of administrative routine.[PARAGRAPH:1]Ashurbanipal was born toward the end of a fifteen-hundred-year period of Assyrian ascendancy. His name in Assyrian is Ashur-bani-apli (the god Ashur has made a[nother] son), affirming that he was not intended to stand in the line of royal accession.[PARAGRAPH:1]His father, Esarhaddon, youngest son of Sennacherib, had become heir when the crown prince, Ashur-nadin-shumi, was deposed by rebels from his position as vassal for Babylon. Esarhaddon was not the son of Sennacherib's queen, Tashmetum-sharrat, but of the West Semitic "palace woman" Zakutu, known by her native name, Naqi'a. The only queen known for Esarhaddon was Ashur-hamat, who died in 672 BC[PARAGRAPH:1]Ashurbanipal grew up in the small palace called bit reduti (house of succession), built by Sennacherib when he was crown prince in the northern quadrant of Nineveh. In 694, Sennacherib had completed the "Palace Without Rival" at the southwest corner of the acropolis, obliterating most of the older structures. The "House of Succession" had become the palace of Esarhaddon, the crown prince. In this house, Ashurbanipal's grandfather was assassinated by uncles identified only from the biblical account as Adrammelek and Sharezer. From this conspiracy, Esarhaddon emerged as king in 681. He proceeded to rebuild as his residence the bit masharti (weapons house, or arsenal). The "House of Succession" was left to his mother and the younger children, including Ashurbanipal.[PARAGRAPH:1]Hisinheritance of Essarhaddon not only included the throne but also his war with Egypt and its lords, the kings of Kush. In 667 he sent an army against it that defeated king Tharqa near Memphis, Ashurbanipal stayed at his capital in Nineveh. At the same time the Egyptian vassals rebelled and the Assyrian army had to crush them. All of the leaders were sent to Nineveh, only Necho I the Prince of Saïs, convinced the Assyrians of his loyalty and was sent back to become king of Egypt. After the death of Tharqa in 664 BC his nephew and successor Tantamani invaded southern Egypt and made Thebe his capital. In Memphis he defeated the other Egyptian princes and Necho may have died in the battle. Another army was sent by Ashurbanipal and again it succeeded in defeating the Kushites. Tantamani retreated to his homeland and stayed there. The Assyrian plundered Thebes and took much booty home with them. How the Assyrian interference in Egypt ended is not certain but Necho's son Psammetichus I gained independence while keeping his relations with Assyria friendly. An interessting Assyrian royal inscription tells us of how the Lydian king Gyges received dreams from the Assyrian god Ashur. The dreams told him that when he submitted to Ashurbanipal he would conquer his foes. After he sent his ambassadors to do so he was indeed able to defeat his Cimmerians enemies. But when he supported the rebellion of one of the Egyptian rebels his country was overrun by the Cilicians.[PARAGRAPH:1]For the time being the dual monarchy went well. For his assignment of his brothers, Ashrubanipal sent a statue of the divinity Marduk with him as sign of good will. Shamsh-shuma-ukin's powers were limited. He performed Babylonian rituals but the official building projects were still executed by his younger brother. During his first years Elam was still in peace as it was under his father. Ashurbanipal even claimed that he sent food supplies during a famine. Around 664 BC the situation changed and Urtaku the Elamite king attacked Babylonia by surprise. Assyria delayed in sending aid to Babylon, this could have been caused for two reasons: either the soothing messages of Elamite ambassadors or Ashurbanipal might simply not have been present at that time. Elamites retreated before the Assyrian troops and in the same year Urtaku died. Urtaku was succeeded by Teumman (Tempti-Khumma-In-Shushinak) who was not his legimate heir. So, many of Elamite princes had to flee from him to Ashurbanipal's court including Urtaku's oldest son Humban-nikash. In 658 BC/657 BC the two empires clashed again. The reason for this was the treasonous province of Gambulu in 664 acting against the Assyrians. Ashurbanipal finally decided to punish them for that. On the other hand, Teumman saw his authority threatened by Elamite princes at the Assyrian court and demanded their extradition. When the Assyrian forces invaded Elam a battle followed at the Ulaya river.[PARAGRAPH:1]Elam was defeated in the battle in which, according to Assyrian reliefs, Teumman committed suicide. Tempti-Khumma-In-Shushinak and Ashurbanipal installed Humban-nikash as king of Madaktu and another prince, Tammaritu, as king of the city Hidalu. Elam was considered as a new vassal of Assyria and so tribute was imposed upon him. With the Elamite problem solved the Assyrians could finally punish Gumbulu and seized its capital. The victorious army marched home taking with them the head of Teumman. In Nineveh, when the Elamite ambassadors saw the head they lost control; one tore out his beard and the other committed suicide but this wasn't enough. As further humiliation the head of the Elamite king was put on display at the port of Nineveh. The death and head of Teumman was depicted multiple times in the reliefs of Ashurbanipal's palace.[PARAGRAPH:1]During the final decade of his rule, Assyria was quite peaceful, but the country apparently faced a serious decline. Documentation from the last years of Ashurbanipal's reign is very scarce, and even the date of his death is not known for certain. The latest attestations of Ashurbanipal's reign are of his year 38 (631 BC), but according to later sources he reigned for 42 years (to 627 BC). Because of the chronological difficulties that arise with his death in 627 Ashurbanipal must have died at an earlier date (probably already in 631) or he could have reigned together with his son and successor Ashur-etil-ilani. Whatever may have been the case, after his death there was a power struggle. The contenders included Ashur-etil-ilani, his brother Sinsharishkun, general Sin-shumu-lishir, and the eventual new king of Babylon, Nabopolassar. Who fought against who is not certain.[PARAGRAPH1]Ashurbanipal is one of the most popular Assyrian kings, as his name is often used for boys within Assyrian communities today.</French>
		<German>[H1]Ashurbanipal[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]King of Assyria[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lived: [\BOLD] c.685 - 627 BC[PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Background:[\BOLD][PARAGRAPH:1]Ashurbanipal, the son of Esarhaddon and Naqi'a-Zakutu, was the last great king of ancient Assyria. He is famous as one of the few kings in antiquity who could himself read and write. Assyrian sculpture reached its apogee under his rule (Northern palace and south-western palace at Nineveh, battle of Ulai). The Greeks knew him as Sardanapalos; Latin and other medieval texts refer to him as Sardanapalus. In the Bible he is called As(e)nappar or Osnapper (Ezra 4:10).[PARAGRAPH:1]During his rule, Assyrian splendour was not only visible in its military power, but also its culture and art. Ashurbanipal created "the first systematically collected library" at Nineveh, where he attempted to gather all cuneiform literature available by that time. A library was distinct from an archive: earlier repositories of documents had accumulated passively, in the course of administrative routine.[PARAGRAPH:1]Ashurbanipal was born toward the end of a fifteen-hundred-year period of Assyrian ascendancy. His name in Assyrian is Ashur-bani-apli (the god Ashur has made a[nother] son), affirming that he was not intended to stand in the line of royal accession.[PARAGRAPH:1]His father, Esarhaddon, youngest son of Sennacherib, had become heir when the crown prince, Ashur-nadin-shumi, was deposed by rebels from his position as vassal for Babylon. Esarhaddon was not the son of Sennacherib's queen, Tashmetum-sharrat, but of the West Semitic "palace woman" Zakutu, known by her native name, Naqi'a. The only queen known for Esarhaddon was Ashur-hamat, who died in 672 BC[PARAGRAPH:1]Ashurbanipal grew up in the small palace called bit reduti (house of succession), built by Sennacherib when he was crown prince in the northern quadrant of Nineveh. In 694, Sennacherib had completed the "Palace Without Rival" at the southwest corner of the acropolis, obliterating most of the older structures. The "House of Succession" had become the palace of Esarhaddon, the crown prince. In this house, Ashurbanipal's grandfather was assassinated by uncles identified only from the biblical account as Adrammelek and Sharezer. From this conspiracy, Esarhaddon emerged as king in 681. He proceeded to rebuild as his residence the bit masharti (weapons house, or arsenal). The "House of Succession" was left to his mother and the younger children, including Ashurbanipal.[PARAGRAPH:1]Hisinheritance of Essarhaddon not only included the throne but also his war with Egypt and its lords, the kings of Kush. In 667 he sent an army against it that defeated king Tharqa near Memphis, Ashurbanipal stayed at his capital in Nineveh. At the same time the Egyptian vassals rebelled and the Assyrian army had to crush them. All of the leaders were sent to Nineveh, only Necho I the Prince of Saïs, convinced the Assyrians of his loyalty and was sent back to become king of Egypt. After the death of Tharqa in 664 BC his nephew and successor Tantamani invaded southern Egypt and made Thebe his capital. In Memphis he defeated the other Egyptian princes and Necho may have died in the battle. Another army was sent by Ashurbanipal and again it succeeded in defeating the Kushites. Tantamani retreated to his homeland and stayed there. The Assyrian plundered Thebes and took much booty home with them. How the Assyrian interference in Egypt ended is not certain but Necho's son Psammetichus I gained independence while keeping his relations with Assyria friendly. An interessting Assyrian royal inscription tells us of how the Lydian king Gyges received dreams from the Assyrian god Ashur. The dreams told him that when he submitted to Ashurbanipal he would conquer his foes. After he sent his ambassadors to do so he was indeed able to defeat his Cimmerians enemies. But when he supported the rebellion of one of the Egyptian rebels his country was overrun by the Cilicians.[PARAGRAPH:1]For the time being the dual monarchy went well. For his assignment of his brothers, Ashrubanipal sent a statue of the divinity Marduk with him as sign of good will. Shamsh-shuma-ukin's powers were limited. He performed Babylonian rituals but the official building projects were still executed by his younger brother. During his first years Elam was still in peace as it was under his father. Ashurbanipal even claimed that he sent food supplies during a famine. Around 664 BC the situation changed and Urtaku the Elamite king attacked Babylonia by surprise. Assyria delayed in sending aid to Babylon, this could have been caused for two reasons: either the soothing messages of Elamite ambassadors or Ashurbanipal might simply not have been present at that time. Elamites retreated before the Assyrian troops and in the same year Urtaku died. Urtaku was succeeded by Teumman (Tempti-Khumma-In-Shushinak) who was not his legimate heir. So, many of Elamite princes had to flee from him to Ashurbanipal's court including Urtaku's oldest son Humban-nikash. In 658 BC/657 BC the two empires clashed again. The reason for this was the treasonous province of Gambulu in 664 acting against the Assyrians. Ashurbanipal finally decided to punish them for that. On the other hand, Teumman saw his authority threatened by Elamite princes at the Assyrian court and demanded their extradition. When the Assyrian forces invaded Elam a battle followed at the Ulaya river.[PARAGRAPH:1]Elam was defeated in the battle in which, according to Assyrian reliefs, Teumman committed suicide. Tempti-Khumma-In-Shushinak and Ashurbanipal installed Humban-nikash as king of Madaktu and another prince, Tammaritu, as king of the city Hidalu. Elam was considered as a new vassal of Assyria and so tribute was imposed upon him. With the Elamite problem solved the Assyrians could finally punish Gumbulu and seized its capital. The victorious army marched home taking with them the head of Teumman. In Nineveh, when the Elamite ambassadors saw the head they lost control; one tore out his beard and the other committed suicide but this wasn't enough. As further humiliation the head of the Elamite king was put on display at the port of Nineveh. The death and head of Teumman was depicted multiple times in the reliefs of Ashurbanipal's palace.[PARAGRAPH:1]During the final decade of his rule, Assyria was quite peaceful, but the country apparently faced a serious decline. Documentation from the last years of Ashurbanipal's reign is very scarce, and even the date of his death is not known for certain. The latest attestations of Ashurbanipal's reign are of his year 38 (631 BC), but according to later sources he reigned for 42 years (to 627 BC). Because of the chronological difficulties that arise with his death in 627 Ashurbanipal must have died at an earlier date (probably already in 631) or he could have reigned together with his son and successor Ashur-etil-ilani. Whatever may have been the case, after his death there was a power struggle. The contenders included Ashur-etil-ilani, his brother Sinsharishkun, general Sin-shumu-lishir, and the eventual new king of Babylon, Nabopolassar. Who fought against who is not certain.[PARAGRAPH1]Ashurbanipal is one of the most popular Assyrian kings, as his name is often used for boys within Assyrian communities today.</German>
		<Italian>[H1]Ashurbanipal[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]King of Assyria[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lived: [\BOLD] c.685 - 627 BC[PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Background:[\BOLD][PARAGRAPH:1]Ashurbanipal, the son of Esarhaddon and Naqi'a-Zakutu, was the last great king of ancient Assyria. He is famous as one of the few kings in antiquity who could himself read and write. Assyrian sculpture reached its apogee under his rule (Northern palace and south-western palace at Nineveh, battle of Ulai). The Greeks knew him as Sardanapalos; Latin and other medieval texts refer to him as Sardanapalus. In the Bible he is called As(e)nappar or Osnapper (Ezra 4:10).[PARAGRAPH:1]During his rule, Assyrian splendour was not only visible in its military power, but also its culture and art. Ashurbanipal created "the first systematically collected library" at Nineveh, where he attempted to gather all cuneiform literature available by that time. A library was distinct from an archive: earlier repositories of documents had accumulated passively, in the course of administrative routine.[PARAGRAPH:1]Ashurbanipal was born toward the end of a fifteen-hundred-year period of Assyrian ascendancy. His name in Assyrian is Ashur-bani-apli (the god Ashur has made a[nother] son), affirming that he was not intended to stand in the line of royal accession.[PARAGRAPH:1]His father, Esarhaddon, youngest son of Sennacherib, had become heir when the crown prince, Ashur-nadin-shumi, was deposed by rebels from his position as vassal for Babylon. Esarhaddon was not the son of Sennacherib's queen, Tashmetum-sharrat, but of the West Semitic "palace woman" Zakutu, known by her native name, Naqi'a. The only queen known for Esarhaddon was Ashur-hamat, who died in 672 BC[PARAGRAPH:1]Ashurbanipal grew up in the small palace called bit reduti (house of succession), built by Sennacherib when he was crown prince in the northern quadrant of Nineveh. In 694, Sennacherib had completed the "Palace Without Rival" at the southwest corner of the acropolis, obliterating most of the older structures. The "House of Succession" had become the palace of Esarhaddon, the crown prince. In this house, Ashurbanipal's grandfather was assassinated by uncles identified only from the biblical account as Adrammelek and Sharezer. From this conspiracy, Esarhaddon emerged as king in 681. He proceeded to rebuild as his residence the bit masharti (weapons house, or arsenal). The "House of Succession" was left to his mother and the younger children, including Ashurbanipal.[PARAGRAPH:1]Hisinheritance of Essarhaddon not only included the throne but also his war with Egypt and its lords, the kings of Kush. In 667 he sent an army against it that defeated king Tharqa near Memphis, Ashurbanipal stayed at his capital in Nineveh. At the same time the Egyptian vassals rebelled and the Assyrian army had to crush them. All of the leaders were sent to Nineveh, only Necho I the Prince of Saïs, convinced the Assyrians of his loyalty and was sent back to become king of Egypt. After the death of Tharqa in 664 BC his nephew and successor Tantamani invaded southern Egypt and made Thebe his capital. In Memphis he defeated the other Egyptian princes and Necho may have died in the battle. Another army was sent by Ashurbanipal and again it succeeded in defeating the Kushites. Tantamani retreated to his homeland and stayed there. The Assyrian plundered Thebes and took much booty home with them. How the Assyrian interference in Egypt ended is not certain but Necho's son Psammetichus I gained independence while keeping his relations with Assyria friendly. An interessting Assyrian royal inscription tells us of how the Lydian king Gyges received dreams from the Assyrian god Ashur. The dreams told him that when he submitted to Ashurbanipal he would conquer his foes. After he sent his ambassadors to do so he was indeed able to defeat his Cimmerians enemies. But when he supported the rebellion of one of the Egyptian rebels his country was overrun by the Cilicians.[PARAGRAPH:1]For the time being the dual monarchy went well. For his assignment of his brothers, Ashrubanipal sent a statue of the divinity Marduk with him as sign of good will. Shamsh-shuma-ukin's powers were limited. He performed Babylonian rituals but the official building projects were still executed by his younger brother. During his first years Elam was still in peace as it was under his father. Ashurbanipal even claimed that he sent food supplies during a famine. Around 664 BC the situation changed and Urtaku the Elamite king attacked Babylonia by surprise. Assyria delayed in sending aid to Babylon, this could have been caused for two reasons: either the soothing messages of Elamite ambassadors or Ashurbanipal might simply not have been present at that time. Elamites retreated before the Assyrian troops and in the same year Urtaku died. Urtaku was succeeded by Teumman (Tempti-Khumma-In-Shushinak) who was not his legimate heir. So, many of Elamite princes had to flee from him to Ashurbanipal's court including Urtaku's oldest son Humban-nikash. In 658 BC/657 BC the two empires clashed again. The reason for this was the treasonous province of Gambulu in 664 acting against the Assyrians. Ashurbanipal finally decided to punish them for that. On the other hand, Teumman saw his authority threatened by Elamite princes at the Assyrian court and demanded their extradition. When the Assyrian forces invaded Elam a battle followed at the Ulaya river.[PARAGRAPH:1]Elam was defeated in the battle in which, according to Assyrian reliefs, Teumman committed suicide. Tempti-Khumma-In-Shushinak and Ashurbanipal installed Humban-nikash as king of Madaktu and another prince, Tammaritu, as king of the city Hidalu. Elam was considered as a new vassal of Assyria and so tribute was imposed upon him. With the Elamite problem solved the Assyrians could finally punish Gumbulu and seized its capital. The victorious army marched home taking with them the head of Teumman. In Nineveh, when the Elamite ambassadors saw the head they lost control; one tore out his beard and the other committed suicide but this wasn't enough. As further humiliation the head of the Elamite king was put on display at the port of Nineveh. The death and head of Teumman was depicted multiple times in the reliefs of Ashurbanipal's palace.[PARAGRAPH:1]During the final decade of his rule, Assyria was quite peaceful, but the country apparently faced a serious decline. Documentation from the last years of Ashurbanipal's reign is very scarce, and even the date of his death is not known for certain. The latest attestations of Ashurbanipal's reign are of his year 38 (631 BC), but according to later sources he reigned for 42 years (to 627 BC). Because of the chronological difficulties that arise with his death in 627 Ashurbanipal must have died at an earlier date (probably already in 631) or he could have reigned together with his son and successor Ashur-etil-ilani. Whatever may have been the case, after his death there was a power struggle. The contenders included Ashur-etil-ilani, his brother Sinsharishkun, general Sin-shumu-lishir, and the eventual new king of Babylon, Nabopolassar. Who fought against who is not certain.[PARAGRAPH1]Ashurbanipal is one of the most popular Assyrian kings, as his name is often used for boys within Assyrian communities today.</Italian>
		<Spanish>[H1]Ashurbanipal[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]King of Assyria[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lived: [\BOLD] c.685 - 627 BC[PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Background:[\BOLD][PARAGRAPH:1]Ashurbanipal, the son of Esarhaddon and Naqi'a-Zakutu, was the last great king of ancient Assyria. He is famous as one of the few kings in antiquity who could himself read and write. Assyrian sculpture reached its apogee under his rule (Northern palace and south-western palace at Nineveh, battle of Ulai). The Greeks knew him as Sardanapalos; Latin and other medieval texts refer to him as Sardanapalus. In the Bible he is called As(e)nappar or Osnapper (Ezra 4:10).[PARAGRAPH:1]During his rule, Assyrian splendour was not only visible in its military power, but also its culture and art. Ashurbanipal created "the first systematically collected library" at Nineveh, where he attempted to gather all cuneiform literature available by that time. A library was distinct from an archive: earlier repositories of documents had accumulated passively, in the course of administrative routine.[PARAGRAPH:1]Ashurbanipal was born toward the end of a fifteen-hundred-year period of Assyrian ascendancy. His name in Assyrian is Ashur-bani-apli (the god Ashur has made a[nother] son), affirming that he was not intended to stand in the line of royal accession.[PARAGRAPH:1]His father, Esarhaddon, youngest son of Sennacherib, had become heir when the crown prince, Ashur-nadin-shumi, was deposed by rebels from his position as vassal for Babylon. Esarhaddon was not the son of Sennacherib's queen, Tashmetum-sharrat, but of the West Semitic "palace woman" Zakutu, known by her native name, Naqi'a. The only queen known for Esarhaddon was Ashur-hamat, who died in 672 BC[PARAGRAPH:1]Ashurbanipal grew up in the small palace called bit reduti (house of succession), built by Sennacherib when he was crown prince in the northern quadrant of Nineveh. In 694, Sennacherib had completed the "Palace Without Rival" at the southwest corner of the acropolis, obliterating most of the older structures. The "House of Succession" had become the palace of Esarhaddon, the crown prince. In this house, Ashurbanipal's grandfather was assassinated by uncles identified only from the biblical account as Adrammelek and Sharezer. From this conspiracy, Esarhaddon emerged as king in 681. He proceeded to rebuild as his residence the bit masharti (weapons house, or arsenal). The "House of Succession" was left to his mother and the younger children, including Ashurbanipal.[PARAGRAPH:1]Hisinheritance of Essarhaddon not only included the throne but also his war with Egypt and its lords, the kings of Kush. In 667 he sent an army against it that defeated king Tharqa near Memphis, Ashurbanipal stayed at his capital in Nineveh. At the same time the Egyptian vassals rebelled and the Assyrian army had to crush them. All of the leaders were sent to Nineveh, only Necho I the Prince of Saïs, convinced the Assyrians of his loyalty and was sent back to become king of Egypt. After the death of Tharqa in 664 BC his nephew and successor Tantamani invaded southern Egypt and made Thebe his capital. In Memphis he defeated the other Egyptian princes and Necho may have died in the battle. Another army was sent by Ashurbanipal and again it succeeded in defeating the Kushites. Tantamani retreated to his homeland and stayed there. The Assyrian plundered Thebes and took much booty home with them. How the Assyrian interference in Egypt ended is not certain but Necho's son Psammetichus I gained independence while keeping his relations with Assyria friendly. An interessting Assyrian royal inscription tells us of how the Lydian king Gyges received dreams from the Assyrian god Ashur. The dreams told him that when he submitted to Ashurbanipal he would conquer his foes. After he sent his ambassadors to do so he was indeed able to defeat his Cimmerians enemies. But when he supported the rebellion of one of the Egyptian rebels his country was overrun by the Cilicians.[PARAGRAPH:1]For the time being the dual monarchy went well. For his assignment of his brothers, Ashrubanipal sent a statue of the divinity Marduk with him as sign of good will. Shamsh-shuma-ukin's powers were limited. He performed Babylonian rituals but the official building projects were still executed by his younger brother. During his first years Elam was still in peace as it was under his father. Ashurbanipal even claimed that he sent food supplies during a famine. Around 664 BC the situation changed and Urtaku the Elamite king attacked Babylonia by surprise. Assyria delayed in sending aid to Babylon, this could have been caused for two reasons: either the soothing messages of Elamite ambassadors or Ashurbanipal might simply not have been present at that time. Elamites retreated before the Assyrian troops and in the same year Urtaku died. Urtaku was succeeded by Teumman (Tempti-Khumma-In-Shushinak) who was not his legimate heir. So, many of Elamite princes had to flee from him to Ashurbanipal's court including Urtaku's oldest son Humban-nikash. In 658 BC/657 BC the two empires clashed again. The reason for this was the treasonous province of Gambulu in 664 acting against the Assyrians. Ashurbanipal finally decided to punish them for that. On the other hand, Teumman saw his authority threatened by Elamite princes at the Assyrian court and demanded their extradition. When the Assyrian forces invaded Elam a battle followed at the Ulaya river.[PARAGRAPH:1]Elam was defeated in the battle in which, according to Assyrian reliefs, Teumman committed suicide. Tempti-Khumma-In-Shushinak and Ashurbanipal installed Humban-nikash as king of Madaktu and another prince, Tammaritu, as king of the city Hidalu. Elam was considered as a new vassal of Assyria and so tribute was imposed upon him. With the Elamite problem solved the Assyrians could finally punish Gumbulu and seized its capital. The victorious army marched home taking with them the head of Teumman. In Nineveh, when the Elamite ambassadors saw the head they lost control; one tore out his beard and the other committed suicide but this wasn't enough. As further humiliation the head of the Elamite king was put on display at the port of Nineveh. The death and head of Teumman was depicted multiple times in the reliefs of Ashurbanipal's palace.[PARAGRAPH:1]During the final decade of his rule, Assyria was quite peaceful, but the country apparently faced a serious decline. Documentation from the last years of Ashurbanipal's reign is very scarce, and even the date of his death is not known for certain. The latest attestations of Ashurbanipal's reign are of his year 38 (631 BC), but according to later sources he reigned for 42 years (to 627 BC). Because of the chronological difficulties that arise with his death in 627 Ashurbanipal must have died at an earlier date (probably already in 631) or he could have reigned together with his son and successor Ashur-etil-ilani. Whatever may have been the case, after his death there was a power struggle. The contenders included Ashur-etil-ilani, his brother Sinsharishkun, general Sin-shumu-lishir, and the eventual new king of Babylon, Nabopolassar. Who fought against who is not certain.[PARAGRAPH1]Ashurbanipal is one of the most popular Assyrian kings, as his name is often used for boys within Assyrian communities today.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_ASHUR_1</Tag>
		<English>He who in his heart utters improprieties against the king - his foundation is but wind, the hem of his garment is but litter. Gather, all the gods of heaven and earth, bless king Ashurbanipal, the circumspect man! I am [OUR_NAME] of the [OUR_EMPIRE].</English>
		<French>He who in his heart utters improprieties against the king - his foundation is but wind, the hem of his garment is but litter. Gather, all the gods of heaven and earth, bless king Ashurbanipal, the circumspect man! I am [OUR_NAME] of the [OUR_EMPIRE].</French>
		<German>He who in his heart utters improprieties against the king - his foundation is but wind, the hem of his garment is but litter. Gather, all the gods of heaven and earth, bless king Ashurbanipal, the circumspect man! I am [OUR_NAME] of the [OUR_EMPIRE].</German>
		<Italian>He who in his heart utters improprieties against the king - his foundation is but wind, the hem of his garment is but litter. Gather, all the gods of heaven and earth, bless king Ashurbanipal, the circumspect man! I am [OUR_NAME] of the [OUR_EMPIRE].</Italian>
		<Spanish>He who in his heart utters improprieties against the king - his foundation is but wind, the hem of his garment is but litter. Gather, all the gods of heaven and earth, bless king Ashurbanipal, the circumspect man! I am [OUR_NAME] of the [OUR_EMPIRE].</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_ATHEAS</Tag>
		<English>Atheas</English>
		<French>Atheas</French>
		<German>Atheas</German>
		<Italian>Atheas</Italian>
		<Spanish>Atheas</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_ATHEAS_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[H1]Atheas[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]King of the Scythian Tribes[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lived: [\BOLD]c.? - 339 BC [NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Background:[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]Beginning in the 4th century BC, several of the nomadic tribes settled to the north of the Black Sea. Kamenskoe Gorodishche (situated in the center of the land separating the Black and Caspian Seas, north of the Caucasus) became the center or capital of the Scythians. King Atheas managed to unite the many Scythian tribes and expanded his domain to the banks of the Danube.[PARAGRAPH:1] In 339 BC, Atheas died while doing battle with Philip of Macedon. Scythia was a power to be reckoned with until the latter part of the 3rd century BC when they were attacked and ultimately absorbed by Thracians from the west and Sarmatians from the east. From hence on, the Scythians are not mentioned in history.</English>
		<French>[H1]Atheas[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]King of the Scythian Tribes[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lived: [\BOLD]c.? - 339 BC [NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Background:[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]Beginning in the 4th century BC, several of the nomadic tribes settled to the north of the Black Sea. Kamenskoe Gorodishche (situated in the center of the land separating the Black and Caspian Seas, north of the Caucasus) became the center or capital of the Scythians. King Atheas managed to unite the many Scythian tribes and expanded his domain to the banks of the Danube.[PARAGRAPH:1] In 339 BC, Atheas died while doing battle with Philip of Macedon. Scythia was a power to be reckoned with until the latter part of the 3rd century BC when they were attacked and ultimately absorbed by Thracians from the west and Sarmatians from the east. From hence on, the Scythians are not mentioned in history.</French>
		<German>[H1]Atheas[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]King of the Scythian Tribes[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lived: [\BOLD]c.? - 339 BC [NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Background:[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]Beginning in the 4th century BC, several of the nomadic tribes settled to the north of the Black Sea. Kamenskoe Gorodishche (situated in the center of the land separating the Black and Caspian Seas, north of the Caucasus) became the center or capital of the Scythians. King Atheas managed to unite the many Scythian tribes and expanded his domain to the banks of the Danube.[PARAGRAPH:1] In 339 BC, Atheas died while doing battle with Philip of Macedon. Scythia was a power to be reckoned with until the latter part of the 3rd century BC when they were attacked and ultimately absorbed by Thracians from the west and Sarmatians from the east. From hence on, the Scythians are not mentioned in history.</German>
		<Italian>[H1]Atheas[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]King of the Scythian Tribes[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lived: [\BOLD]c.? - 339 BC [NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Background:[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]Beginning in the 4th century BC, several of the nomadic tribes settled to the north of the Black Sea. Kamenskoe Gorodishche (situated in the center of the land separating the Black and Caspian Seas, north of the Caucasus) became the center or capital of the Scythians. King Atheas managed to unite the many Scythian tribes and expanded his domain to the banks of the Danube.[PARAGRAPH:1] In 339 BC, Atheas died while doing battle with Philip of Macedon. Scythia was a power to be reckoned with until the latter part of the 3rd century BC when they were attacked and ultimately absorbed by Thracians from the west and Sarmatians from the east. From hence on, the Scythians are not mentioned in history.</Italian>
		<Spanish>[H1]Atheas[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]King of the Scythian Tribes[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lived: [\BOLD]c.? - 339 BC [NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Background:[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]Beginning in the 4th century BC, several of the nomadic tribes settled to the north of the Black Sea. Kamenskoe Gorodishche (situated in the center of the land separating the Black and Caspian Seas, north of the Caucasus) became the center or capital of the Scythians. King Atheas managed to unite the many Scythian tribes and expanded his domain to the banks of the Danube.[PARAGRAPH:1] In 339 BC, Atheas died while doing battle with Philip of Macedon. Scythia was a power to be reckoned with until the latter part of the 3rd century BC when they were attacked and ultimately absorbed by Thracians from the west and Sarmatians from the east. From hence on, the Scythians are not mentioned in history.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_ATHEAS_1</Tag>
		<English>I am [OUR_NAME] of the [OUR_EMPIRE]. If you must needs come to blows with us speedily, look about you, and behold our fathers' tombs. Attempt to meddle with them and you shall see whether or not we will fight with you.</English>
		<French>I am [OUR_NAME] of the [OUR_EMPIRE]. If you must needs come to blows with us speedily, look about you, and behold our fathers' tombs. Attempt to meddle with them and you shall see whether or not we will fight with you.</French>
		<German>I am [OUR_NAME] of the [OUR_EMPIRE]. If you must needs come to blows with us speedily, look about you, and behold our fathers' tombs. Attempt to meddle with them and you shall see whether or not we will fight with you.</German>
		<Italian>I am [OUR_NAME] of the [OUR_EMPIRE]. If you must needs come to blows with us speedily, look about you, and behold our fathers' tombs. Attempt to meddle with them and you shall see whether or not we will fight with you.</Italian>
		<Spanish>I am [OUR_NAME] of the [OUR_EMPIRE]. If you must needs come to blows with us speedily, look about you, and behold our fathers' tombs. Attempt to meddle with them and you shall see whether or not we will fight with you.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_KHOSRAU</Tag>
		<English>Khosrau I</English>
		<French>in French</French>
		<German>in German</German>
		<Italian>in Italian</Italian>
		<Spanish>in Spanish</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_KHOSRAU_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[H1]Khosrau I[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Shah of Persia[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lived: [\BOLD]501-579 CE[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2]Little is known of the early life of Khosrau beyond legends. One story says that when Khosrau's father, King Kavadh, took refuge with the Hephthalites, eastern neighbours of Iran, on the way (near the town of Nishapur) he married a peasant's daughter, who gave birth to Khosrau. At his father's death Khosrau did not at first succeed him, but in a struggle for the throne he was successful and put to death his brothers. At the end of his father's reign, great social disorders had occurred because of a religious revolution of a sect called the Mazdakites. Khosrau first restored order and then launched reforms to transform the declining Sasanian empire.[PARAGRAPH:2]The reform of taxation was the most important of his actions, and it was probably copied from the Roman system inaugurated by the emperor Diocletian. Previously in the Sasanian empire taxes had been levied on the yield of land; Khosrau established a fixed sum rather than a yearly variation. Other taxes were introduced that brought stability to the income of the state and were also fairer to those who paid the taxes. Khosrau's program of taxes lasted into Islamic times. He also reorganized the Sasanian bureaucracy, and the system of ministries, or divans, under a prime minister is said to have been initiated by him. He was fortunate during most of his reign in having a capable prime minister called Bozorgmehr, who became famous in story and legend for his wisdom and abilities. Under Khosrau the process of decentralization of the power of the monarch was reversed, and the lower aristocracy, or knights, called dihqans, grew in importance at the expense of the great feudal lords, who had been more powerful under Khosrau's predecessors. It is difficult to know how many changes really can be attributed to Khosrau's reign and how many are arbitrarily assigned to him because of his place in history. Whether the religiously sanctioned division of society into priests, warriors, bureaucracy, and common folk was codified under his reign, as claimed by some sources, is difficult to determine.[PARAGRAPH:2]Khosrau also reorganized the army and appointed four chief commanders to guard the four frontiers of Iran. On the frontier against the Byzantines and their Arab allies in the Syrian Desert, against the peoples of the steppes of southern Russia at the town of Derbent between the Caucasus Mountains and the Caspian Sea, and to the east of the sea in the present Turkmen steppes, Khosrau built defensive walls. The army, however, did not remain on the defensive, for Khosrau's reign is noted for his wars against the Byzantines. In 540 Antioch was conquered and held for a short time by Khosrau. He brought many prisoners from Antioch and settled them in a new town near his capital of Ctesiphon, modeled on old Antioch. In the east, Khosrau, in alliance with the Turks, a new power in Central Asia, crushed the Hephthalites, and he established a hegemony over many of their principalities. The Sasanian frontier in the east reached the Amu Darya (Oxus River) during his reign. He also fought extensively in Armenia and Lazica in the Caucasus. Furthermore, under his reign a Sasanian army conquered Yemen. Khosrau relied on a professional army more than his predecessors, who had summoned feudal levies when they set out to war.[PARAGRAPH:2]Khosrau was also a great patron of culture, and in 529, when the ancient academy of Athens was closed, a number of Greek philosophers migrated to the Sasanian empire, where they were well received by the ruler. The later famous medical school of Gondeshapur was probably started in Khosrau's reign, and the famous physician Burzoe is supposed to have been sent to India by Khosrau to gather Sanskrit books of learning to be translated into the Middle Persian language. The game of chess reportedly was also brought by him from India. Astronomy and astrology flourished at the court of Khosrau, and one star table (called the zij-i Shahriyar), which was the basis of many later Islamic tables, is said to have originated during the reign of Khosrau. Several works of Middle Persian, such as the Book of Deeds of Ardashir (Karnamak), are attributed to this period. Likewise, some scholars claim that the codification of the Avesta, the sacred book of the Zoroastrian religion, as well as the creation of a special Avestan alphabet to record the text, took place at the order of Khosrau. Further, it is supposed that the stories and legends of ancient Iran were gathered into a Khwatay-namak ("Book of Kings") in the time of Khosrau and thus provided the source for Ferdowsi's immortal epic much later. Some of the names found in Ferdowsi's Shah-nameh appear among the royal family of Khosrau, which indicates at the least an interest on the part of the monarch in ancient legends.[PARAGRAPH:2]Perhaps more than fact, the stories told about Khosrau have made his name famous in history. Almost any pre-Islamic structure in Iran whose origin is unknown will be attributed to Khosrau by the simple folk. Undoubtedly he built many bridges, roads, and palaces, but much more is assigned to him in legend. The famous palace with the huge arch, called Taq Kisra, in Ctesiphon, near modern Baghdad, is said to date from Khosrau I, but this is uncertain. Several collections of wise sayings of this monarch, as well as stories about him, have been preserved in Arabic or New Persian versions. In them his reputation for justice as well as wisdom is constantly cited. The splendour of the court and the glory of his reign provided models for the later 'Abbasid court in Baghdad, and many of the institutions established by Khosrau were maintained in Islamic times, when Khosrau was hailed as the model pre-Islamic ruler to be emulated by Muslim princes.[PARAGRAPH:2]</English>
		<French>in French</French>
		<German>in German</German>
		<Italian>in Italian</Italian>
		<Spanish>in Spanish</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_REFUSE_TO_TALK_LEADER_SAMPLE_LEADER_1</Tag>
		<English>Your Refuse to talk response</English>
		<French>Your Refuse to talk response</French>
		<German>Your Refuse to talk response</German>
		<Italian>Your Refuse to talk response</Italian>
		<Spanish>Your Refuse to talk response</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_NO_PEACE_LEADER_SAMPLE_LEADER_1</Tag>
		<English>Your refuse to peace talks response</English>
		<French>Your refuse to peace talks response</French>
		<German>Your refuse to peace talks response</German>
		<Italian>Your refuse to peace talks response</Italian>
		<Spanish>Your refuse to peace talks response</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_GREETINGS_ATT_FR_LEADER_SAMPLE_LEADER_1</Tag>
		<English>Your Friendly Hello Response</English>
		<French>Your Friendly Hello Response</French>
		<German>Your Friendly Hello Response</German>
		<Italian>Your Friendly Hello Response</Italian>
		<Spanish>Your Friendly Hello Response</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_GREETINGS_ATT_FUR_LEADER_SAMPLE_LEADER_1</Tag>
		<English>Your Unfriendly Hello Response</English>
		<French>Your Unfriendly Hello Response</French>
		<German>Your Unfriendly Hello Response</German>
		<Italian>Your Unfriendly Hello Response</Italian>
		<Spanish>Your Unfriendly Hello Response</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_DEMAND_TRIBUTE_POWER_WEAKER_SAMPLE_LEADER_1</Tag>
		<English>Your Demands to another civ when you are weaker then they are</English>
		<French>Your Demands to another civ when you are weaker then they are</French>
		<German>Your Demands to another civ when you are weaker then they are</German>
		<Italian>Your Demands to another civ when you are weaker then they are</Italian>
		<Spanish>Your Demands to another civ when you are weaker then they are</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_DEMAND_TRIBUTE_POWER_EQUAL_SAMPLE_LEADER_1</Tag>
		<English>Your Demands to another civ when you are Equal to power as they are</English>
		<French>Your Demands to another civ when you are Equal to power as they are</French>
		<German>Your Demands to another civ when you are Equal to power as they are</German>
		<Italian>Your Demands to another civ when you are Equal to power as they are</Italian>
		<Spanish>Your Demands to another civ when you are Equal to power as they are</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
		<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_DEMAND_TRIBUTE_POWER_STRONGER_SAMPLE_LEADER_1</Tag>
		<English>Your Demands to another civ when you are stronger then they are</English>
		<French>Your Demands to another civ when you are stronger then they are</French>
		<German>Your Demands to another civ when you are stronger then they are</German>
		<Italian>Your Demands to another civ when you are stronger then they are</Italian>
		<Spanish>Your Demands to another civ when you are stronger then they are</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_MASINISSA</Tag>
		<English>Masinissa</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_MASINISSA_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[H1]Masinissa[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]King of Numidia[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Reign: [\BOLD]c.240 - c.148 BCE[NEWLINE][NEWLINE][NEWLINE]Needs to be written.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_MASINISSA_1</Tag>
		<English>Greetings. I am [OUR_NAME] of the [OUR_EMPIRE]. Do you come in peace?</English> <!-- Generic -->
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_REFUSE_TO_TALK_LEADER_MASINISSA_1</Tag>
		<English>I have nothing to say to you.</English> <!-- Generic -->
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_NO_PEACE_LEADER_MASINISSA_1</Tag>
		<English>It is much too late for peace now, [CT_NAME].</English> <!-- Generic -->
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_GREETINGS_ATT_FR_LEADER_MASINISSA_1</Tag>
		<English>Welcome, [CT_NAME]. What is it that you wish to discuss?</English> <!-- Generic -->
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_GREETINGS_ATT_FUR_LEADER_MASINISSA_1</Tag>
		<English>You try my patience, [CT_NAME]. Be brief.</English> <!-- Generic -->
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_DEMAND_TRIBUTE_POWER_WEAKER_LEADER_MASINISSA_1</Tag>
		<English>The [OUR_EMPIRE] is in need of assistance. Can you help us, [CT_NAME]?</English> <!-- Generic -->
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_DEMAND_TRIBUTE_POWER_EQUAL_LEADER_MASINISSA_1</Tag>
		<English>Consider this the price of [OUR_CIV_SHORT]'s continued patience.</English> <!-- Generic -->
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_DEMAND_TRIBUTE_POWER_STRONGER_LEADER_MASINISSA_1</Tag>
		<English>For the sake of your civilization's continued survival, I suggest that you comply with our demands.</English> <!-- Generic -->
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_URUKAGINA</Tag>
		<English>Urukagina</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_URUKAGINA_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[H1]Urukagina[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]King of Lagash[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Reign: [\BOLD]c.2400 BCE[NEWLINE][NEWLINE][NEWLINE]Uru-ka-gina was King of the city-states of Lagash and Girsu in Mesopotamia, and the last ruler of the 1st Dynasty of Lagash. He assumed the title of king, claiming to have been divinely appointed, upon the downfall of his corrupt predecessor, Lugalanda.[NEWLINE]He is best known for his reforms to combat corruption, which are sometimes cited as the first example of a legal code in recorded history. Although the actual text has not been discovered, much of its content may be surmised from other references to it that have been found. In it, he exempted widows and orphans from taxes; compelled the city to pay funeral expenses (including the ritual food and drink libations for the journey of the dead into the lower world); and decreed that the rich must use silver when purchasing from the poor, and if the poor does not wish to sell, the powerful man (the rich man or the priest) cannot force him to do so.[NEWLINE]He also participated in several conflicts, notably a losing border conflict with Uruk. In the seventh year of his reign, Uruk fell under the leadership of Lugal-Zage-Si, énsi of Umma, who ultimately annexed most of the territory of Lagash and established the first reliably documented kingdom to encompass all of Sumer. The destruction of Lagash was described in a lament (possibly the earliest recorded example of what would become a prolific Sumerian literary genre), which stressed that "the men of Umma ... committed a sin against Ningirsu. ... Offence there was none in Urukagina, king of Girsu, but as for Lugal-Zage-Si, governor of Umma, may his goddess Nisaba make him carry his sin upon his neck". Lugal-Zage-Si himself was soon defeated and his kingdom was annexed by Sargon of Akkad.</English>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>
