<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!-- bluepotato: Wonder texts go here -->
<Civ4GameText>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_GREAT_COTHON</Tag>
		<English>Great Cothon</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Grand Cothon</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>Der Gro&#223;e Cothon</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_GREAT_COTHON_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>The [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Great Cothon[COLOR_REVERT] add a bonus production to every water tile worked by its city. It increases its city's odds of generating a [COLOR_UNIT_TEXT]Great Merchant[COLOR_REVERT].</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_GREAT_COTHON_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]The cothon at Carthage was divided into a rectangular merchant harbor followed by an inner protected harbor reserved for military use only. This inner harbor was circular and surrounded by an outer ring of structures divided into a series of docking bays for ship maintenance, along with an island structure at its center that also housed navy ships. Each individual docking bay featured a raised slipway. Above the raised docking bays was a second level consisting of warehouses where oars and rigging were kept along with supplies such as wood and canvas. On the island structure there existed a raised 'cabin' where the admiral in command could observe the whole harbor along with the surrounding sea. Altogether the inner docking complex could house up to 220 ships. The entire harbor was protected by an outer wall and the main entrance could be closed off with iron chains.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_TRAJANS_COLUMN</Tag>
		<English>Trajan's Column</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_TRAJANS_COLUMN_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]Trajan's Column (Italian: Colonna Traiana) is a Roman triumphal column in Rome, Italy, that commemorates Roman emperor Trajan's victory in the Dacian Wars. It was probably constructed under the supervision of the architect Apollodorus of Damascus at the order of the Roman Senate. It is located in Trajan's Forum, built near the Quirinal Hill, north of the Roman Forum. Completed in AD 113, the freestanding column is most famous for its spiral bas relief, which artistically describes the epic wars between the Romans and Dacians (101-102 and 105-106). Its design has inspired numerous victory columns, both ancient and modern.The structure is about 30 metres (98 ft) in height, 35 metres (125 ft) including its large pedestal. The shaft is made from a series of 20 colossal Carrara marble drums, each weighing about 32 tons, with a diameter of 3.7 metres (11 ft). The 190-metre (625 ft) frieze winds around the shaft 23 times. Inside the shaft, a spiral staircase of 185 stairs provides access to a viewing platform at the top. The capital block of Trajan's Column weighs 53.3 tons, which had to be lifted to a height of c. 34 m.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_RUSTAM</Tag>
		<English>Naqsh-e-Rustam</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_RUSTAM_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]Naqsh-e Rustam, also referred to as Necropolis, is an archaeological site located about 12 km northwest of Persepolis, in Iran. Naqsh-e Rustam lies a few hundred meters from Naqsh-e Rajab. The oldest relief at Naqsh-i Rustam is severely damaged and dates to c. 1000 BC. It depicts a faint image of a man with unusual head-gear and is thought to be Elamite in origin. The depiction is part of a larger mural, most of which was removed at the command of Bahram II. The man with the unusual cap gives the site its name, Naqsh-e Rostam, &quot;Picture of Rostam&quot;, because the relief was locally believed to be a depiction of the mythical hero Rostam. The triumph of Shapur I (c. 241-272):  is the most famous of the Sassanid rock reliefs, and depicts Shapur's victory over two Roman emperors, Valerian and Philip the Arab. A more elaborate version of this rock relief is at Bishapur.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_RUSTAM_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>[COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Naqsh-e-Rustam[COLOR_REVERT] increases likelihood a [COLOR_UNIT_TEXT]Great General[COLOR_REVERT] will be produced, increases cultural output, and increases the likelihood a [COLOR_UNIT_TEXT]Great Artist[COLOR_REVERT] will be generated.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_GREAT_BATH</Tag>
		<English>Great Bath</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_GREAT_BATH_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]The "great bath" is without doubt the earliest public water tank in the ancient world. The tank itself measures approximately 12 meters north-south and 7 meters wide, with a maximum depth of 2.4 meters. Two wide staircases lead down into the tank from the north and south and small sockets at the edges of the stairs are thought to have held wooden planks or treads. At the foot of the stairs is a small ledge with a brick edging that extends the entire width of the pool. People coming down the stairs could move along this ledge without actually stepping into the pool itself.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE][TAB] The floor of the tank is water tight due to finely fitted bricks laid on edge with gypsum plaster and the side walls were constructed in a similar manner. To make the tank even more water tight, a thick layer of bitumen (natural tar) was laid along the sides of the tank and presumably also beneath the floor. Brick colonnades were discovered on the eastern, northern and southern edges. The preserved columns have stepped edges that may have held wooden screens or window frames. Two large doors lead into the complex from the south and other access was from the north and east. A series of rooms are located along the eastern edge of the building and in one room is a well that may have supplied some of the water needed to fill the tank. Rainwater also may have been collected for this purposes, but no inlet drains have been found.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE][TAB] The floor of the tank is water tight due to finely fitted bricks laid on edge with gypsum plaster and the side walls were constructed in a similar manner. To make the tank even more water tight, a thick layer of bitumen (natural tar) was laid along the sides of the tank and presumably also beneath the floor. Brick colonnades were discovered on the eastern, northern and southern edges. The preserved columns have stepped edges that may have held wooden screens or window frames. Two large doors lead into the complex from the south and other access was from the north and east. A series of rooms are located along the eastern edge of the building and in one room is a well that may have supplied some of the water needed to fill the tank. Rainwater also may have been collected for this purposes, but no inlet drains have been found.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE][TAB] Most scholars agree that this tank would have been used for special religious functions where water was used to purify and renew the well being of the bathers.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_GREAT_BATH_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>The [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Great Bath[COLOR_REVERT] grants +2 population to all newly built cities.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_GREAT_BATH_HELP</Tag>
		<English>[ICON_BULLET]New cities receive +2 population</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_ASHURBANIPAL_LIBRARY</Tag>
		<English>Ashurbanipal's Library</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_ASHURBANIPAL_LIBRARY_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]The Royal Library of Ashurbanipal, named after Ashurbanipal, the last great king of the Assyrian Empire, is a collection of thousands of clay tablets and fragments containing texts of all kinds from the 7th century BCE. Among its holdings was the famous Epic of Gilgamesh.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE][TAB]Ashurbanipal was known as a tenacious martial commander; however, he was also a recognized intellectual who was literate, and a passionate collector of texts and tablets. As an apprentice scribe he mastered both the Akkadian and the Sumerian languages He sent scribes into every region of the Neo-Assyrian Empire to collect ancient texts. He hired scholars and scribes to copy texts, mainly from Babylonian sources.[NEWLINE][TAB]Ashurbanipal used war loot as a means of stocking his library. Because he was known for being cruel to his enemies, Ashurbanipal was able to use threats to gain materials from Babylonia and surrounding areas. Ashurbanipal's intense interest in collecting divination texts was one of his driving motivations in collecting works for his library. His original motive may have been to "gain possession of rituals and incantations that were vital to maintain his royal power."[NEWLINE][TAB]The royal library consists of approximately 30,000 tablets and writing boards with the majority of them being severely fragmented. It can be gleaned from the conservation of the fragments that the number of tablets that existed in the library at the time of destruction was close to two thousand and the number of writing boards within the library can be placed at a total of three hundred. The majority of the tablet corpus (about 6,000) included colloquial compositions in the form of legislation, foreign correspondences and engagements, aristocratic declarations, and financial matters. The remaining texts contained divinations, omens, incantations and hymns to various gods, while others were concerned with medicine, astronomy, and literature. For all these texts in the library only ten contain expressive rhythmic literary works such as epics and myths.[NEWLINE][TAB]Nineveh was destroyed in 612 BCE by a coalition of Babylonians, Scythians and Medes, an ancient Iranian people. It is believed that during the burning of the palace, a great fire must have ravaged the library, causing the clay cuneiform tablets to become partially baked. This potentially destructive event helped preserve the tablets. As well as texts on clay tablets, some of the texts may have been inscribed onto wax boards which, because of their organic nature, have been lost.</English>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_ASHURBANIPAL_LIBRARY_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>[COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Ashurbanipal's Library[COLOR_REVERT] doubles its city's research output, and increases the likelyhood a [COLOR_UNIT_TEXT]Great Scientist[COLOR_REVERT] will be generated.</English>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>
